Before we get into the code and start correcting for
在我们开始编码并纠正失真前
distortion, let's get some intuition as to how this distortion occurs.
首先让我们初步了解失真是如何发生的
Here's a simple model of a camera called the pinhole camera model.
这里是一个简单的针孔相机模型
When the camera forms an image,
当摄像头生成图像时
it's looking at the world similar to how our eyes do.
其观察世界的方式与人眼相似
By focusing the light that's reflected off of objects in the world.
就是通过聚焦物体所反射的光进行成像的
In this case through a small pinhole, the camera focuses the light that's
在本例中 通过一个小小的针孔
reflected off of a 3D traffic sign, and forms a 2D image
摄像机将一个三维交通标志的反射光聚焦
at the back of the camera or a sensor or some film would be placed.
并在摄像头后部放置的传感器或胶片上 生成一张二维图像
In fact the image it forms here will be upside down, and
实际上 这里生成的图像是翻转倒置的
reversed because rays of light that enter from the top of an object
因为从物体顶部反射的光线
will continue on that angled path through the pinhole and
通过针孔后 会继续沿相同角度前进
end up at the bottom of the formed image.
最终在所生成图像的底部被捕获
Similarly, light that reflects off the right side of an object
类似地 物体右方所反射的光
will travel to the left of the formed image.
会到到达所生成图像的左方
In math this transformation from 3D object points, P of X, Y, and Z.
在数学中 这种从三维物体图像点 P(X, Y, Z)
To 2D image points, P of just X, and
到二维图像点 P(X, Y) 即只有 X 和 Y 的转换
Y is done by a transformative matrix called the camera matrix.
是通过一个变换矩阵完成的 这个矩阵被称为相机矩阵
Which I'll call C for camera and
这里我用 C 表示相机矩阵
we'll need this to calibrate the camera later on.
我们稍后需要用这个矩阵来校准摄像机
However, real cameras don't use tiny pinholes like this,
然而 真实的相机并非使用小孔成像原理进行聚焦
they use lenses to focus multiple light rays at a time.
它们使用的是能一次性聚焦大量光线的镜头
Which allows them to quickly form images.
这使得其能迅速生成图像
But lenses can introduce distortion too.
但是 镜头会产生失真
Light rays often bend a little too much or
光线通常会在摄像机镜头的边缘
too little at the edges of a curved lens of a camera, and this creates the effect
出现过大或过小幅度的弯曲
we looked at earlier that distorts the edges of images.
从而产生 我们之前看到的图像边缘扭曲的效果
So that lines or objects appear, more or less, curved than they actually are.
因此 线条或者物体会比其真实情况呈现出或多或少的弯曲
This is called radial distortion, and it's the most common type of distortion.
这种失真被称为径向畸变 是最常见的失真类型
Another type, is tangential distortion, if the camera's lens is not aligned
另外一种类型的失真称为切向畸变 如果摄像机镜头未能
perfectly parallel to the imaging plane where the camera film or
与摄像机胶片或者传感器所在的成像平面平行
sensor is, this makes an image look tilted.
图像看起来就会倾斜
So that some objects appear further away or closer than they actually are.
结果就是 某些物体会比其真实情况显得更远或者更近
And this is tangential distortion.
这就是切向畸变
There are even example of lenses that purposefully distort images like fisheye
甚至还有利用镜头刻意扭曲图像的例子
or wide angle lenses which keep radial distortion for stylistic effect.
例如鱼眼镜头或者广角镜头 这样做是为了保留径向畸变的风格效果
But for our purposes we are using this images
不过 在我们的课程里 我们使用这些图像
to position ourself driving car and eventually steer it the right direction.
是为了在驾驶汽车时进行定位 以保证汽车的行驶方向正确
So we need undistorted images that accurately reflect
因此 我们需要去除图片的失真
our real world surroundings.
以精确反映真实环境
Luckily, this distortion can generally be captured by five numbers called
所幸的是 这种失真一般可以通过 5 个参数进行消除
distortion coefficients, whose values reflect the amount of radial and
这些数字叫做畸变系数 它们的值反映了图像中的径向畸变
tangential distortion in an image.
和切向畸变
In severely distorted cases, sometimes even more than
在严重失真的情况下 有时甚至需要 5 个以上的
five coefficients are required to capture the amount of distortion.
畸变系数 才能确定所有图像失真信息
If we know these coefficients,
如果我们知道这些系数
we can use them to calibrate our camera and undistort our images.
那么我们可以运用其对摄像头进行标定并矫正图像
And the mathematical details of correcting for
关于修正失真的详细数学步骤
distortion are in the notes below.
可以参考下方的注解
Next we'll see how to get these coefficients and calibrate a camera.
接下来 我们会学习如何获取这些系数并标定摄像头